<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ## will be replaced by two new lines in explanations -->
<SqQuiz author="Tarun Pradhaan" quizname="Pure Experiences" quizversion="1.0" sqversion="1.0">
   <section id="1" name="Knowledge">
      <question q="What am I?">
         <options>
            <option op="A man/woman with a particular name, related to someone, have a particular race, nationality and profession">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>You are in the grip of ignorance, identified with concepts and beliefs.##Names, relations, professions are just attributes of a body. They can be changed at will and hence are not the essence of who you are.##The essence can be defined as that which remains unchanged when one or the other attribute is changed. For example changing your name or gender will not magically create a new you. So these tags are not you essentially.##Most importantly you are not a physical body, it changes too, it is a flow of matter from environment and back. Ask yourself - what is your essential nature, which never changes?</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Human being having a spirit">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>You still identify with a form, although you are open to the possibility of formless.##It is more accurate to say that I am a spirit having a human form.##Or even more accurately - my experience of "I" is a pure consciousness, a witnessing emptiness that is witnessing an experience named human form or human life. </explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Pure consciousness aka the Self">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>You are Self realized.##The essence of "I" is consciousness, which is unchanging background of all experiences, it is the universal experiencer. The "I" is also an experience, which is the mind identifying with consciousness.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A body-mind complex made up of matter">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>You are a rational being, but have not seen your essence.##Behind this seemingly logical idea is the assumption that body is made up of "something" and mind is a product of it. When you try to find matter, if you try to experience it, you will not find it. Matter is just change perceived via senses. The mind makes up an illusion of matter out of the pure perceptions. So both body and mind are nothing but experiences without any substance which is independent of mind.##In other words, all experience is information. Clearly, I am the perceiver of that information, I am the consciousness. Explore on this path, it takes you to amazing knowledge.</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="Essential nature of the existence is">
         <options>
            <option op="Oneness">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>You have achieved the union. There are bits and pieces of ignorance that are left.##We can say that Oneness is the ground of everything. However in order to exist as Oneness, the experiencer must dissolve, and along with it the experience also dissolves. In other words nothing "exists". So paradoxically, the existence always needs to be a duality of an experience and an experiencer.##Oneness is beyond existence, where it lies latent, waiting to be expressed.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Nondual">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>You have achieved the union. You have reached the end of knowledge.##The mind cannot know the Oneness in a way it knows other objects or experiences, so it stops at no-two. However, it is possible to be Oneness, which is what everything is anyway. I am that Oneness.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Unknowable">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>You have the understanding of the vastness, but not of the Oneness. Too much mind.##The essential nature of everything that exists is the Self, aka pure consciousness. All existence happens on the screen of consciousness, and there is only one of it.##Explore the Self and you will know.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Creator and Creation">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>You are in the grip of beliefs gathered from others. All you need to do is question them.##These are the concepts behind which exists no experience. If you look with a clean slate, our experience is that the existence simply is. Mind comes up with such ideas in order to explain the whole of the existence in terms of cause and effect. Everyday objects have causes, and so it assumes that there needs to be a cause for the whole of our experience.##Existence is an experience. This experience is being witnessed by an experiencer (the pure consciousness), and is nothing but its own modulations. Changes in existence have causes, experience itself is uncaused.##Experience more and seek guidance of an experienced teacher.</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="World is">
         <options>
            <option op="An illusion or a dream">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>You are wise and detached. However, see that the world is also you, and you are not an illusion.##These are merely metaphors that try to describe the experience of a world. The experience is like a mirage, a dreamlike event. The underlying reality of a dream is the dreamer. The reality of the world is the beholder of the world.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Real">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>You have not questioned enough. A seeker needs to question everything.##The word "real" is merely a way to classify experiences based on a chosen criteria. What gets classified as real is dependent on what criteria you choose to apply. Since everyone has their own criteria, the classification is purely subjective.##So what you think is real is purely imaginary. One can make anything real by choosing a suitable set of criteria. There is a delusion that criteria for reality or truth are written in stone somewhere. In practice those who are in power impose their criteria in order to manipulate people more effectively.#Question everything.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A part of the Universal mind">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>You have a good understanding of what is going on.##The world, which is an experience, and although appears like a dream, is just me. It is also Self. However, it is a special experience, which is bound by laws and is very limited.##If you explore the whole set of experiences, they range from purely mental to purely physical. However one can easily club them into a single structure, which is more like a mind. This is the universal mind, and this world, including the bodies is a tiny part of it.##The universal mind is also me. This is the whole picture.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Merely a creation of consciousness, a play">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>You have seen the illusion of world. You know its nature.##It is a play, but not a creation. Play being a metaphor for incessant and mysterious change. But consciousness does not create, it merely witnesses the play. The play creates itself. Or more accurately, the play is, just like the consciousness simply is. World needs no creator.</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="Best way to gain knowledge is">
         <options>
            <option op="Direct experience">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>You have the key to knowledge. You will progress fast.##Knowledge can be defined as organized or structured experience. Knowledge resides in memory and produces the intention to act. All actions come out of knowledge, so it is critical that we be very certain of it.##However knowledge has its limits, as mind is limited, hence at the existence is fundamentally unknowable.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A Guru or a teacher">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>You are fortunate to have Guru. You will be shown the right path.##A Guru, remover of darkness, is necessary for the beginners on the spiritual path. The mind is totally immersed in ignorance, so someone who has come out of it is needed.##However, it is the Grace not Guru which enables our journey our of darkness. The one who's time has arrived cannot be stopped, Guru or no Guru.##Just do not blindly believe what a Guru tells you, try to know it via your own experience. Guru simply points to the knowledge, it is our job to get it.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Books or scriptures or other media">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>You are starting to take interest in spirituality.##These are least reliable ways of gaining knowledge. Perhaps the opinion of crowd is the only one that is less reliable than books. Remember that anyone can write a book, the words in the book are not the truth necessarily. And just because it is on internet does not make it true.##However, if you choose carefully, there are some real gems. You need to ensure that the author speaks from his own experience, and is not merely parroting some old texts.##Even better, try to meet the authors, if you can. You will progress faster. A book cannot talk back, it cannot correct you, and you cannot ask questions to a book. Still a book is our best friend, when there is no teacher.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Logic and reasoning">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>You are making a good use of the mind. Mind is tool for gaining knowledge, and logic and reason are its important parts.##Logical inference words well when something cannot be experienced directly. First preference should be given to actual experience, else it becomes armchair knowledge. Logic, when not based on experience produces absurd results, and a rational mind can be fooled by simply making a theory very logical and sophisticated.</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="Truth is">
         <options>
            <option op="Anything that can be proven by empirical evidence">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>You are a rational seeker.##You will get at the truth most of the time via empirical verification. However whether you choose to classify your experiences as true or false depends on subjective criteria. Keep an eye on the criteria, everyone has their own set of criteria, so the word "truth" loses meaning very quickly.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Logical, consistent or mathematical">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>You have a good definition of truth. But it is very limited.##Experiences can be seemingly illogical, and especially mental experiences rarely follow mathematical laws. Some experiences happen only once and have no consistency. Hence this view of the truth will leave out a major portion of your experiences. That will limit your progress.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A majority decision based on utility">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>You are a practical person. But this view may keep you away from the truth.##People can something as true depending on the utility and how it helps them to survive well or act reasonably. However a wider experience shows that these so called truths are convenient models or assumptions which people adopt to make the lives simple. They became truths just because a majority of people called them so.##Its not what majority of them say, and its not utility based. History shows us that "truth" keeps changing. Explore.</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A categorization based on a set of reasonable subjective criteria">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>You are free from truth.##One can classify any statement as true or false based on a list of criterion. These criteria can be very strict and reasonable, but they are always subjective. Everyone and anyone can have their own criteria. So truth for one may not be the truth for the other.##A seeker does not act on truth, he acts on knowledge, which can only come from experience. Your own experience is your truth.##Truth is private, fluid and made up.</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
   </section>
   <section id="2" name="Cultivation">
   <question q="My meditation routine:">
      <options>
         <option op="I do not meditate">
            <score>0</score>
            <explanation>Probably you are on some other path?##Meditation is a term which is related to the mind. It can be changing the mind to something better or can be simply controlling its wild behaviour. It can be freeing the mind from ignorance or beliefs, or it can be augmenting the mind with new knowledge.##So either you have a very specific view of what meditation is, or you are not interested in cultivation. Seek guidance.</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="All day or an hour to few hours per day">
            <score>3</score>
            <explanation>You have found a good meditation which suits you.##An ideal kind of meditation is effortless, does not need exotic poses or techniques, can be done while conducting the everyday affairs of worldly life, and produces the exact change in your mind that is your goal. Simple awareness or mindfulness are good examples. We can remain aware and conscious all day and all night.</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Few minutes or sometimes whenever I am free">
            <score>2</score>
            <explanation>You have began your cultivation. However it does not seem to be your priority at present.##Meditation is generally misunderstood as some complicated technique which needs to be learned for many years. There are some of those, no doubts, but meditation can be simple, like being aware of your mind, speech and action. Simple does not mean less powerful.##If you are not interested in the specific meditation you are doing sometimes, seek some other simpler one. Consult your Guru.</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Only when my mind is in a disturbed state">
            <score>1</score>
            <explanation>You have found some use of meditation.##Meditation is not an escape. It is not a medicine for the mind. It is a powerful tool for cultivation. The right kind of meditation brings peace and freedom.##Meditation, if it numbs the mind, distracts it from life issues or sends the mind in some la-la land, is of no use. Why not try something which frees you from getting disturbed forever?</explanation>
         </option>
      </options>
   </question>
   <question q="My practice involves">
      <options>
         <option op="Introspection">
            <score>3</score>
            <explanation>"You have found the best kind of spiritual practice. You are on a direct path.##Introspection is seeing within, as all knowledge and answers lie within. This inherent knowledge is covered up with the dust of ignorance, which is the cause of all suffering and bondage. Introspection is a technique to uncover the ignorance, and to destroy it by seeing what is rather than what is assumed."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Yoga, pranayam or Kundalini">
            <score>2</score>
            <explanation>"You are on the path of Hatha yoga.##You have found a path. However, if you are doing it just because everyone else is doing it, or if you do it for something superficial like health benefits or blissful experiences, then you need to review your practices. Consult your Guru, try the direct path first."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Practice?!?">
            <score>0</score>
            <explanation>"You have not yet realized the importance of it.##Or you are already a Mahayogi. Practice is a term that is very broad, there can be many kinds of spiritual practices. Depends on one's goal. It can be a whole lifestyle.##If someone is interested in cultivation, taking up some practice can help."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Astral Projection">
            <score>1</score>
            <explanation>"You are on the evidence gathering phase.##It is well and good as long as it is not just for fun or other superficial reasons. This practice provides a direct experience of the universal mind and can be utilized to connect with a guru or guides. It may help in cultivation, but is not necessary.##Remember your purpose here, do not make astral your life goal."</explanation>
         </option>
      </options>
   </question>
   <question q="I read">
      <options>
         <option op="Anything I find interesting and educational">
            <score>2</score>
            <explanation>"You have a good taste.##But there seems to be lack of goal. Someone who is very focused on a goal would read something very specific, not just anything.##Sometimes the boring spiritual text can be most useful."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Non fiction and biographies">
            <score>1</score>
            <explanation>"You have a broad choice. Still looking for something?##It is a sign of curious mind, but points to a lack of direction and purpose. A seeker is very focused, and is not interested in trivia. Well, there is nothing bad there, but one would want to utilize all of his free time or reading time in seeking knowledge via reading."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Philosophical and spiritual books">
            <score>3</score>
            <explanation>"You are very focused.##You are one of those hardcore seekers who do not waste even one second of their life in reading useless texts. Some of the books can be very entertaining, and some may be full of knowledge, but you need those that help you progress towards your goal."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Stories, newspaper and magazines">
            <score>0</score>
            <explanation>"You have found a good way to entertain the ego.##A serious seeker would want to stay away from fluff, especially when it is difficult to spare time from one's busy schedule. An intelligent seeker would not touch the sources of negativity, such as newspapers.##This choice also shows that a good amount of attachment to worldly matters is still present. A seeker is the one, who's whole interest has shifted to the Self. If is does not help to achieve his spiritual goals, he does not read it."</explanation>
         </option>
      </options>
   </question>
   <question q="I attend meetings with people that are">
      <options>
         <option op="Satsangs or spiritual talks/Q&amp;A's, where I can get knowledge">
            <score>3</score>
            <explanation>"A good way to spend time indeed.##Not only is it motivating and brings joy, you get to meet the fellow seekers who may be on similar paths.##Usually a seeker prefers solitude, but it can be energizing if you meet the right kind of people."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Job/Business meetings where I can get new contracts and connections">
            <score>0</score>
            <explanation>"You are still in the rat race.##Try a minimalist life for a change, see if it works better for your spiritual goal, if there are any. If it doesn't, you have unfulfilled material needs, in which case you need to take care of your job and business.##Re-evaluate your life, question your tendencies."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Friendly and casual, I like to be in a positive company, just be happy">
            <score>2</score>
            <explanation>"You are sensitive, positive and social.##A great way to spend time. Meditation and practices can get monotonous and boring. Try meeting spiritual people, they are not very difficult to be friends with. You will not only enjoy their company, you will also learn a lot."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Family gatherings where I can stay close to my own relatives, I feel love">
            <score>1</score>
            <explanation>"You are a family person. Loving, caring and charming.##Have you checked that you are not attached? Are you doing it to get rid of the loneliness? Do you feel more secure and safe in family rather than in a cave? Do you have this urgent need to feel loved by others?##If you say yes to most of these psychoanalysis kind of questions, then you need help. Consult your Guru asap."</explanation>
         </option>
      </options>
   </question>
   <question q="I often visit">
      <options>
         <option op="Shops and malls, sometimes bars">
            <score>0</score>
            <explanation>"You are attached to a material lifestyle.##Nothing wrong in that, but probably you are just waking up. Why else would you take this crazy SQ quiz?"</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Temples and places of worship">
            <score>1</score>
            <explanation>"You are following your conditioning. A belief is separation or supernatural powers exists.##A seeker is free from all belief systems, including his own personal one. If you still feel attracted towards traditions and organized religions, you are on a path of devotion.##Be careful, take what you think is useful. Devotion is a personal affair, do not get brainwashed by the powerful ruling class."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Aashrams">
            <score>3</score>
            <explanation>"You have found a place where you always wanted to be.##Aashram means a shelter, a sanctuary. A new comer gets the proper environment to grow here.##Anyhow, be careful about getting involved. You are there for peace of mind, not to climb the ladder, not to make the owners rich, not to be abused or controlled.##Some Aashrams are just commercial places these days. Choose wisely."</explanation>
         </option>
         <option op="Places of natural beauty">
            <score>2</score>
            <explanation>"You have found peace of mind.##You do not like crowded places and nature makes you feel one with everything. Its purity and innocence attracts you.##When you are with mother nature, your nature mimics her. Her language is silence, she is beautiful and perfect beyond description. You remain free from both good and bad qualities. You remain what you are, when you are with nature."</explanation>
         </option>
      </options>
   </question>
   </section>
   <section id="3" name="Surrender">
      <question q="I am surrendered to">
         <options>
            <option op="God">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are on the path of devotion.##Unless the concept of God is imposed upon you by social conditioning, you probably know what you are doing.##Now all you need to do is realize what this concepts means, what does it point to.##If you do not know what exactly you are surrendered to, it can be an uphill battle."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Self">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You are egoless.##The so called separate self has vanished for you. You are one with the Self, identified with nothing else but the Self.##You are in the flow, there is no resistance or suffering, no pleasures or pain, you are in peaceful bliss."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Guru">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"Your progress is now ensured.##A Guru takes the responsibility to take you to your destination, to bring you to your goals, whatever they are. He knows the way, and since you follow him in total surrender, like a child follows his father, you will surely reach there.##Realize that the Guru is just an external form of the Self. Complete your surrender."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="No one">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You like it your own way.##Which cannot be totally bad. However, this means more struggle, more effort, more time, and risk of falling back.##Its never late to ask for help or assistance. Help comes in many forms. If you think it is like taking on a burden on favour, you can always return it by helping others. It is win-win."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="Surrender means">
         <options>
            <option op="Obey the will of a greater power">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You have great faith.##Be careful whom you trust. And when you see someone or something as more powerful than you are, you put yourself at a lesser place. There is only One, and that One is also my Self.##You can cut to the chase."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Put down the gun and hands above the head">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You are very much involved in worldly activities.##The meaning of surrender will be obvious to you when you pick up a spiritual path. It does not mean obeying some force, it does not mean bondage or acting on the will of the others.##It is mostly overcoming one's own resistances. It is a recognition of one's own faults and taking actions to correct them."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Follow a Guru, never question him">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You have a real Guru finally.##Questioning your Guru, or getting your doubts cleared does not mean that you are not surrendered. Unless you do it with an attitude that I know more than you, or when there is a doubt.##Skepticism is a required quality for a seeker, gullibility is not helpful.##Usually an experienced Guru will see the difference between a curious and skeptical student, and an arrogant closed minded one. He can also see when you become a yes man, and he may shock you out of it.##Surrender to the knowledge, not to the holder of the knowledge. A Guru can only point to the knowledge."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Give up the resistance of the mind towards knowledge">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"Your surrender is complete and meaningful.##There are no more dark corners in your mind now. When you see a bit a darkness, you acknowledge it at once, and brighten it with knowledge, which comes almost instantly.##Nothing is blocking your path."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="When life delivers pain and suffering">
         <options>
            <option op="I offer the other cheek">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are very kind and humble.##Probably it is good manners or conditioning, but check if this attitude is taking you nearer to your goals. Or see if you have any meaningful goals at all.##Life is a series of experiences, it is teaching us something. Wake up and see it."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I try to fix things as much as I can">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You are practical, rational and energetic.##Have you ever wondered, no matter how much you fix things, there is always some more things that need fixing?##Have you noticed that things, especially people fall back into the old patterns very quickly? How many people can you fix in this short life time? Are you missing the one who needs most fixing?"</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I accept, learn, let go and move on">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You are highly focused. A real karmyogi.##You do not let any event, any experience go waste. To you it does not matter if the experience is that of a pleasure or of pain, you learn from all of them.##You also do not stick to any of them, you get up, dust off, and keep going. Sometimes you see the hidden opportunity in events where others see only difficulty and misery."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I fight and deliver the double back to whoever is responsible">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You are brave. Although still in dark. In total grip of egoic impulses.##There are no others, life is an experience, only we are responsible for what happens in it. If I do not see why it happened, why life delivered pain or suffering, and what changes are needed in myself so that it never happens again, it is a waste of life."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="When someone with more knowledge and experience than my own tells me something">
         <options>
            <option op="I always keep that in mind and teach it to others too">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You are a good learner.##You are doing a great service too. Giving away the knowledge is the greatest donation and greatest service.##Now it is the right time to implement it too. Practice what you teach.##Be careful whom you teach, all may not be ready for it."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I listen with respect and attention, and try to implement it or experiment with it. Share it only if the student is worthy of knowledge.">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You are a ripe seeker.##You are as good as a Guru. You know that the knowledge can be gained only via an experience, and you are not afraid to implement it, experiment with it, and know it in depth.##You also use discretion when you disseminate the knowledge. Some people are so deep in ignorance that they are threatened by it, do not like it or become fearful. Knowledge can harm some people instead of benefiting them. One needs to know only that which is required for him at that stage. Not all are worthy of all knowledge."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I argue if I think it is erroneous and correct that person">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You have little tolerance for being wrong.##Argument is an egoic action, it is about who knows better, who is superior. Argument is not an exchange of knowledge and light, it is an exchange of gunfire.##You can point out a mistake or correct it, if that is what is asked for, else you listen and leave."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I also try to tell that person something of value, to return the favour">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are friendly and helpful.##Your ego wants to show what you know. You do not want to appear ignorant and stupid. You do it in the guise of returning the favour.##The best favour you can return is to implement what you have learnt, practice it yourself. Be grateful. The one who gave you that knowledge will notice it, will be happy and will respect you even more.##If someone needs to know something, they will ask you."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="When I am proven wrong with respect to my words or actions">
         <options>
            <option op="I accept and ask for forgiveness">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You are humble.##Accepting that I can be wrong is only the first step. Next one is to correct it, change yourself. The one who is pointing to it is probably hinting that something needs to change."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I feel irritated and angry">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are resisting. Anyhow, you can see your ignorance bared.##Ego can become defensive when it senses a threat to its cherished beliefs. It springs into action and defends them as it does not want to be seen as defeated. Best defense is attack, so anger arises.##See the ancient and outdated mechanisms of the mind, overcome them. Surrender to knowledge."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I ignore it and continue">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You are asleep.##Some people are so deep in darkness that simple words suggesting a mistake are ineffective. Or the intelligence is not enough to even see how they are wrong. Eventually this ignorance causes suffering and then the learning happens.##As a first step, try to stop and see why someone says you are wrong. Ask for help or explanation."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I am thankful for it and correct myself">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You have the courage and intelligence. You are soaking up the knowledge like a sponge.##Learning from the experience of others is intelligence, admitting our own ignorance is courage and correcting oneself is the right action.##Try asking for comments on your other views also, see if any of them are also wrong."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
   </section>
   <section id="4" name="Behaviour">
      <question q="My goal in life is to">
         <options>
            <option op="Serve others, make this planet a beautiful place">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are distracting yourself.##The planet is already very pretty and people are perfect as they are. Our desires to change everything that is so big and external are ineffective. Change comes from within. Change yourself. Find your flaws and clear them.##One person with a tiny capability and tiny lifespan cannot do much, but imagine if everyone corrected only themselves, there can be a mass improvement overnight. Lead by example."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Just be happy and free by destroying my ignorance">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You are enlightened and free.##Experience is all there is. There is nothing more to what we call as life. It is just the Self expressing as various forms, and hence nothing needs to be done.##Ignorance veils our blissful nature, and its destruction unveils infinite happiness and sets us free."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Get as much money and as many partners as I can">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You are engaged in hoarding and mating behaviour.##Explore what it means to be a human. We are much more than animals. Human life begins when the basic needs are met. More of survival is just fueling our animal nature, it eventually brings suffering for the self and for others too.##Rise above your ego."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Liberation from suffering and transmigration in bodies">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You have a high and noble goal.##When you know your essential nature, you will see that you are already free. You are never born, and you never die or take rebirth.##These are the activities of the causal body or karmic memories or jiva, which is just a part of the mind. You have identified with it, and hence feel the need to be liberated.##You can be free now, right here."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="My attitude towards people is">
         <options>
            <option op="Kind and compassionate">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You have a good heart.##You see others are suffering and you rush to help them. You see others as your own form.##You still have a need to behave in a specific way."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Indifferent, unless they need my help">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are a good citizen, mostly minding your own business.##You see others as separate from yourself."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Depends on what I can get back from them, good for good and bad for bad">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You like to trade. You see people as either a source of pleasure or a threat.##Ego can be very selfish. Try not to expect too much from others, give whenever you can."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Unconditional love">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You are one with everyone.##Other people are just expressions of the Self, which is you. Allowing them as they are, with all their qualities and imperfections is unconditional love. Not expecting, giving that which is needed, and allowing all situations, good or bad, is a sign of unconditional love."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="I buy things when">
         <options>
            <option op="I really need them">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You are a minimalist, and very efficient.##You dislike clutter, which reflects your own state of mind - free from clutter. You manage your finances carefully, as wasted money is wasted time. Time is the real wealth for a seeker, not objects.##More time means more practice, more peace."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I can afford them">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Your income is the only limit for your impulses.##You believe that objects can bring happiness, especially the shiny new ones.##If you do not need it, its not worth it. Simply because you can but something should not mean that you get it. Greed does not bring happiness, it is a suffering in itself."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I desire them intensely, not impulsively">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You have found a balance between need and hobbies.##Presence of desires still point to your remaining ignorance. See from where the desires to own unnecessary objects arise from. Free yourself."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="It can make me look better or rich, it raises my social status and standard of living">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are a worldly person, but you are honest.##There is nothing wrong in being worldly, and using objects to achieve worldly goals. Ensure that you have higher goals.##Once you rise above mere survival, you will see the frivolity of such behaviour."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="When someone I know dies">
         <options>
            <option op="I feel sad in my heart and often cry">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are deeply attached to the forms.##Body is a disposable part of something greater. Life is a continuous experience, it never stops. Death is also an experience. Death belongs to the body, not to the Self, it merely sheds old clothes.##See your true nature, which is the same for everyone also."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I sympathize and offer condolences, provide help if needed">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You are a sensitive and friendly person.##However the sympathy means that you enforce the illusion of the body in other minds.##Death is not an occasion for sadness, nothing of value is lost when a pile of organic matter fails. It is not you, you are not the body, nobody is a body. It is a part of the experience that is born and then destroyed."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I remain unmoved, steady and calm">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You have realized your true nature. You are completely detached from bodies.##Only those who see the body as themselves, or those who think that the body is important, or those who cling to the body however old and sick it gets, are the one's who suffer from the event of a death."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I am terrified and stay away, pray that it never happens to me">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"You have a fear of dying.##Ego does not like to die. It is terrified of its disappearance and does everything possible to remain alive.##Death is a natural process. It is just dropping of body, which is a disposable part of us.##We shed it just like we shed old clothes. You need to explore more to see the truth of it."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="If someone insults me">
         <options>
            <option op="I try to forgive and forget, do not get attached or suffer">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"A very reasonable action indeed.##Have you ever noticed why someone would want to insult you? Was it your rudeness, was it your speech, or were you simply in a bad company?##It can be an accident, but if it happens frequently, see what needs to change in yourself."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I insult back, that teaches them a lesson and protects me in future">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"That's an egoic reaction, a defense mechanism.##Mimicking someone else's bad behaviour surely won't improve you. When you also act violently, there is no difference between you and the other person.##Installing fear in others does not ensure your safety, it raises the risk. A fearful person is more likely to attack back.##You cannot change others by force, you are the one who needs to learn."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I avoid that person in future, stay away from all toxic people">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"You are careful but also fearful. Afraid of getting hurt by mere words.##You still harbour a hate for others, which eats you from within.##Avoiding does not mean that you are now protected, you are as vulnerable as you were. You need to armour yourself, so that you can face any situation. Words should not affect you.##Usually it is the ego that reacts to insults, you are not the ego, you are the witness of it, you remain unaffected. Realize this, and be unmoved."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="I do a self analysis and try to see why that happened, and correct myself">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You have the right attitude. You know where to place the responsibility.##You do not blame others. You accept the situation, and try to understand where you went wrong. You are not really concerned with others, or why they behaved that way, you are concerned about yourself, you want to know how you got into such situation, where is the need for correction. You already know others in and out, they are sleeping egos, so you do not feel any need to react."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
   </section>
   <section id="5" name="Powers">
      <question q="I have the power to">
         <options>
            <option op="Read another's mind">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"All minds are connected. Everyone can do that, just that they are not aware of it. It is a minor power."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Heal diseases">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"This is a big achievement. Body is an extension of the mind. And all minds are connected. Intention can have a great effect on it."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Manifest anything">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You have mastered the creation. Worlds are just patterns in the mind. You have a great control on the creative power of the mind."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Make anyone smile">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Social abilities are useful too. A seeker goes beyond worldly things."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="I'd like to have a power">
         <options>
            <option op="To kill anyone just by willing it">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Many destructive and violent people would want it. There can be a lot of anger and fear here. Irrational thoughts are a sign of disturbed mind."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="To be immortal, super rich and beautiful">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"Ego has hijacked the spiritual goals and have turned them into a means to satisfy its puny wishes."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="To be super intelligent and know everything">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"Its a nobel desire. One does not need a spiritual power to be that. Mind is very powerful as it is. Explore."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="To be able to create universes and lifeforms">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You have aligned with the flow of universal mind. We are budding creators. You will reach there quickly."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="Spiritual powers are">
         <options>
            <option op="An obstacle on my path">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"Surely they can be obstacles, they can distract a seeker from achieving his true goals.##However, it is not the powers, it is the mind of the seeker himself that is an obstacle. It is getting tangled into the lure of powers."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Very useful way to gain advantage over others and destroy evil from this planet">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"The survivor in us, the ego, is strong. It has overpowered the mind, and now you cannot see clearly.##Others are not your concern, only you are. Planet is already perfect, just like everything else is."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Great evidence against materialism and perhaps help to create new technologies">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"There is a presence of a desire to defeat others, show them who is right. This is an egoic desire. Powers have nothing to do with social situations or beliefs of others.##Desire to use powers for worldly gain or to accomplish worldly tasks is a sign of ignorance and over attachment with the worlds."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A tool to progress faster on my path">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"That is the best use of power. When an ordinary seeker turns them into distractions and entertainment, a real seeker uses them to progress further on his path.##Powers are just unveiling of what we already are. We are all powerful, the ignorance has rendered us limited. Our goal is not powers, but destruction of ignorance. We can use powers to achieve it faster."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="Best way to get powers is">
         <options>
            <option op="Worship of powerful deities">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"While this can be a shortcut, it can have undesirable consequences. Dependency on someone who is more powerful than you are is inviting the trouble.##Also, it does nothing for your own evolution. You remain the same old ignorant person, moreover, now on someone else's mercy."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Spiritual transformation which happens naturally as I progress">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"Powers or Siddhis are a side effect of spiritual evolution. We are returning home and remembering who we are.##Powers are just unveiling of what we already are. We are all powerful, the ignorance has rendered us limited. Our goal is not powers, but destruction of ignorance. We can use powers to achieve it faster."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Occult practices">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"You are ambitious and brave. It can be a difficult route.##In order to cause a change, one must change himself. Try transforming yourself into who you are."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Join government or military or corporate giants">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Power over the self is a good alternative compared to power over others. Only fearful and violent people want power over others, they are terrified of losing their status and hence gather a crowd of minions to protect themselves."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="My attitude towards people who claim to have powers is that of">
         <options>
            <option op="Jealousy">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Someone who is incapable of achieving something, resorts to jealousy and envy. This is a sign that the ego has taken over higher mind. This is an attitude of a loser."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Skeptical">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"This is an indicator of a healthy mind. You are rational and can think clearly.##It is not important that someone is claiming something, it is important that you investigate it yourself. There is always something new to learn.##Rigid skepticism will halt your progress."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Indifference">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"A seeker is not really concerned with what other have or do not have. Claims do not bother him, he is after evidence.##Anyhow if someone else has some powers means nothing to someone who is steadily progressing on his own path."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Respect">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"This can be a sign that you easily believe others. It is not the powers, but what a person does with them, should decide how much you respect him.##Anyone can get powers, but only those who use them to bring others out of the darkness deserve our respect."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
   </section>
   <section id="6" name="Experience">
      <question q="My current experience as a human is that of">
         <options>
            <option op="Oneness which is mysterious and unknowable">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"This is the true nature of all the experience.##Mind creates divisions and produces the illusion of many in one. Mind assigns names and relations among the many and calls it knowledge. Such knowledge is ignorance.#When this is seen, oneness remains. It is, there is nothing to know there."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="An experiencer that is changeless and an experience that is ever changing">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"What you are seeing are the aspects of just one. Just like the one coin has two faces, oneness can be seen as two opposites of the change and the changeless.##Mind creates this apparent division. See and know."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A non-physical mind witnessing an illusory world">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"Mind is non-physical and the world is illusory, but it is the consciousness that is the only witness. It witnesses the mind too, which is as illusory as the world.##Discriminate clearly between the mind and the consciousness."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A body with intelligent and self-aware brain in a real physical world">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Points to deep ignorance. These are just blind beliefs. Brain and body are extensions of the mind. Mind has intelligence. It creates a world out of pure change. It produces patterns out of pure information.##Real is whatever you define real, it is not something absolute, it is a subjective choice. Others have fed you their notions of what is real, and you have uncritically accepted them. It is time to wake up and examine your beliefs."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="My experience of oneness was">
         <options>
            <option op="Very extraordinary, never seen before, want to have it again">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"The everyday ordinary experience is of oneness too. If there is a strong belief that only extraordinary experiences are that of oneness, then the seeker is perhaps still ignorant, and haven't really seen the oneness yet."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Ordinary, just a realization that it was always so and always is">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"Oneness is just like lifting of a veil. It is here now, and it was always here. Our mind covered it up with its incessant activities. Our identification with the mind and body made us forget what we are.##You are back home now. It is nice and peaceful here."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Never had such an experience, I am trying though">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"The mind is trying and that is the reason you cannot experience it. Keep the mind away, see how it is creating the divisions, see that there is no separation."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="There is no such thing, its a blind belief">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"It is very easy to ignore that which is so obvious. Oneness is like water for a fish. Points to a lack of interest in exploring. Question everything. Question your own beliefs too."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="When I see another person, an animal, a plant or a rock, I see">
         <options>
            <option op="An illusion">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"Surely they are illusory. However what is the real nature of this illusion? Who is behind the curtains? Does dismissing experience as mere illusion brings you most satisfaction, or you feel a need to know more?"</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Myself">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"When it is all one, and it is the Self, then everything can be nothing but the Self.##Identification shifts from the body to the mind and then to the consciousness, and ultimately to everything. Everything experience is just me looking at me."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A person, animal, plant and a rock">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"That is what the mind tells you. There is a need to question deeply. What is the reality behind these names and forms? Why do they appear as forms with a name pointing to them?"</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="A play of life and death">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"Shows a presence of random concepts. The mind is tangled in ideas borrowed from others. A product of random encounters, not a sign of directed and intentional seeking. An experienced teacher can help clear your mind."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="My dreams and deep sleep states are">
         <options>
            <option op="Fully aware in dreams, unaware in deep sleep">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"That is a great progress already. Explore the possibilities. Deep sleep is not an absence of consciousness. To believe otherwise is an obstacle towards experiencing a conscious sleep state."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Unaware in dreams and deep sleep">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"This is the condition of almost everyone who is not seeking. Points to an absence of awareness in waking state too."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Occasional awareness in dreams and less often in deep sleep">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"There is some potential here. When you remain intensely aware in waking state, the mind will continue to do so in other states. Practice makes you perfect."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Fully aware in both dream and deep sleep states">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"You have achieved the forth. It will be easy for you to remain aware when the great sleep finally arrives."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
      <question q="My waking state is">
         <options>
            <option op="Mostly awareness and peace, intentional actions and speech">
               <score>3</score>
               <explanation>"Points to a full awakening. A good control over actions and thoughts. The mind is blissful. This is the ideal state to be in."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Mostly in past or in future, many thoughts and desires on which I act as quickly as possible">
               <score>0</score>
               <explanation>"Points to a total lack of awareness. The mind is disturbed, untamed. The thoughts are random and uncultivated. Actions are impulsive. You need help."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Occasional moments of awareness and habitual actions rest of the time">
               <score>2</score>
               <explanation>"Points to a lack of practice and interest. Or perhaps you are just starting.##Set up reminders to the self to remain aware. Try suitable techniques. Take interest and be curious of what the mind is doing. Be alert in any environment. Bring back awareness every time you slip. Remember."</explanation>
            </option>
            <option op="Aware and peaceful as long as external situations are favorable, else I plunge into darkness">
               <score>1</score>
               <explanation>"Points to a dependency on external situations, perhaps presence of rigid rituals in practice, or a lack of practice.##Break your habits. Challenge yourself to be aware in all situations, whether it is a noisy and violent social situation or the usual boring state of sleep."</explanation>
            </option>
         </options>
      </question>
   </section>
</SqQuiz>